In this lecture, we'll talk about control hazards and exceptions.
Control Dependents will complete our discussion of pipeline hazards.
We'll discuss what control hazards are, different ways of resolving them, and then finally wrap
up with exception handling.
First let's define what we mean by program control dependence.
An instruction Y is control dependent on an instruction X if X determines whether or not
Y will be executed.
And this is specifically due to conditional branches.
A branch instruction needs to be executed to see if it will or will not be taken and
figure out which instruction to fetch next.
Many instructions that follow the branch are control dependent on it.
Here's an example program with a pair of branches with control dependence listed.
Instruction 0 is branch not equal with the target of I3.
This means instructions 1 and 2 are executed if and only if this branch is not taken, which
makes them control dependent on instruction 0.
Since the branch not equal targets I3, this means instructions 3 or 4 are not control dependent
on instruction 0 since they are executed regardless of the values in S1 and S3.
Instruction 4 is a branch equal instruction.
If the branch is taken, then the PC jumps back to instruction 0, which means instructions
0 through 4 are all control dependent on that branch.
Technically, control dependence doesn't need to be preserved to ensure program correctness.
It's okay for us to execute some instructions that shouldn't have been executed as long
as those speculative instructions still preserve data dependencies and don't cause new exceptions.
A control hazard occurs when an incorrect instruction is fetched into the pipeline because
the outcome of a branch instruction has not yet been resolved.
This is possible in our five-stage pipeline because branches don't get resolved until
a later stage.
In our base implementation shown here, the branch's decision is generated in the memory
stage.
Specifically, the PC will be updated to the correct instruction address after the branch's
memory stage.
Let's explore control hazards with a toy example.
Say that this branch equal instruction will be taken because T0 and T1 are indeed equal.
The issue is that we don't know if it's taken until the end of cycle 4 when the branch
instruction has finished the memory stage.
Our processor kept updating PC to PC plus 4 and three additional instructions were fetched
and pushed into the pipeline before the branch was resolved.
Next we'll discuss the ways we can resolve control hazards.
The first and simplest solution is to continue to fetch the next instruction, that is PC
plus 4, until the branch is resolved.
This is effectively predicting and hoping that the branch is not taken.
However, if the branch is to be taken, we need to flush or turn into no ops, these instructions
that we incorrectly fetch before they change any program visible state, like data memory
or the register file.
This is shown in the pipeline diagram as equal signs in cycle 5.
In this case, flushing looks like we instead chose to stall three cycles.
This approach is a form of speculation where we intentionally execute instructions before
we've confirmed that they should be executed to improve performance.
That means that if most branches are not taken most of the time, then the performance loss
that happens when they are is minimized.
To reduce the performance overhead, let's left shift the branch resolution as early
as possible.
This leverages the fact that in our MIPS ISA, we only need to support simple equality comparisons
in our branches, so they don't affect the cycle time by much.
We can choose to resolve branches at the execute or even in the decode stage, as shown here.
Let's first compute the branch target PC in the decode stage.
This is simple since the target only depends on the instruction word, which was already
available at that stage.
We will have to instantiate an adder as we can no longer use the existing one in the
ALU.
The comparison adds a bit of delay since it's a combinatorial logic cloud that comes after
the end of the decode stage, which is after the gate delay of reading registers out of
the register file in the second phase of the clock due to register bypass.
Depending on the comparison type, the result of the comparison is effectively the PC source
control signal that selects between PC plus 4 and the branch target for the next PC.
The last thing we must attend to is the flush.
If the branch is taken as determined by the control logic, then the IFAD pipeline register
must be cleared as the instruction currently in the fetch stage has been incorrectly fetched.
We must propagate a NOOP instead of the incorrect instruction.
Let's go back to our earlier example.
Now the branch is resolved in cycle 2 when the branch equal instruction is at the decode
stage.
This only needs to flush one instruction instead of three, which is the load instruction, which
gets cleared upon entering the decode stage in cycle 3.
Here's an animation of how the control hazard is resolved.
We start in cycle 2 where we fetch the load instruction speculatively, predicting that
the branch will not be taken.
But if it is taken, then the load instruction gets converted to a NOOP in the next cycle
and the correct subtract instruction is then fetched.
The NOOP then propagates through the rest of the pipeline as if the load never happened.
But now what about raw hazards?
Unlike other instructions, we now need the register operands in the decode stage for
branch instruction, which was previously only needed in the ALU stage, which is why
we created the execute to execute forwarding and memory to execute forwarding.
In this example, register T1 is read by the branch equal instruction, but it's not ready
until after the add executes.
One solution is to stall and implement full forwarding back to the decode stage.
At cycle 3, the branch needs to stall since execute is still working on the add.
The add's results will be ready in cycle 4 and can be forwarded to the comparison logic
in the branch's decode stage.
This is an example of execute to decode forwarding.
Memory to decode forwarding can be implemented in a similar way.
Some early architectures, including MIPS and digital signal processors, had what's known
as a branch delay slot instead of adding hardware complexity for resolving control hazards.
A branch delay slot is an instruction immediately after a branch that is unconditionally executed
regardless of whether or not the branch is taken.
This puts the onus on the software to handle control hazards with legal instructions instead
of imposing hardware complexity.
In the example program shown, the add instruction is currently in the delay slot.
This means that whether or not the branch is taken, the add will be executed to completion
and will never be flushed.
In this example, the add instruction in the branch delay slot is illegal because it violates
program correctance by introducing a false data dependence on registered T5.
If the branch were taken, then the subtract instruction is supposed to read a different
value of T5, not the one produced by the add, which wouldn't be executed in the original
program.
We have two options for filling the branch delay slots.
The first is to insert a no op into the program at the branch delay slot.
No ops don't affect program state and thus are always safe to insert.
With this, the add instruction will only be executed when the branch is not taken, which
is the correct program behavior.
The better option would be to fill the branch delay slot with an instruction that needed
to be executed anyway.
This avoids the loss cycle due to the no op.
In this example, we can move the load that preceded the branch equal to after, as the
load did not write any registers that the branch equal depended on reading.
This program would produce correct results whether the branch were taken or not.
A common approach to resolving control hazards is dynamic branch prediction.
This is implemented in most modern processors, including the ones in your tablet, laptop,
or phone that you're probably watching this video on.
The idea is to predict the branch outcome or direction, which is either taken or not
taken.
This prediction is typically employed in the fetch stage, which is cycle one in the pipeline
diagram, so that upon the next cycle, the subtract instruction can be immediately fetched
if the branch is predicted to be taken.
Obviously the branch target address is also either computed earlier or predicted in some
way using branch target buffers, but this is a more advanced topic that we won't be
covering in this course.
So in this example, by the end of cycle two, we will know whether or not the branch is
indeed taken.
In this case, our prediction is correct, so we don't have to do anything else.
If our branch predictor instead mispredicts thinking that the branch won't be taken,
then after cycle two, the add instruction will be flushed as usual.
In the end, we'd have the same single cycle penalty as in the previous predict.taken approach.
The simplest way to implement branch direction prediction is to use a branch history table
or BHT with one-bit predictions.
Bits of the current PC, which is the address of the branch instruction itself, are used
to index into the BHT and select an entry.
In this example, an 8-bit BHT is indexed by three bits of the PC.
As an aside, for MIPS, we typically ignore the two least significant bits of the PC.
Why is that?
So now once we've selected an entry in the BHT, each entry contains a one-bit prediction
to indicate taken or not taken.
The bit is then updated according to the FSM or finite state machine on the right.
This FSM looks more complex than it really is.
The branch table will show one if a branch at that address alias was taken last time
and zero if it was not.
Let's see how this works with an example.
Here, we're predicting the branch equal instruction upon each iteration of the loop.
In the first iteration, we read the prediction from the BHT.
In this case, let's say the BHT entry is zero.
So we predict that we will not take the branch.
Then let's say it turns out that the branch is actually taken.
So we need to update the prediction accordingly to predict taken next time.
This algorithm continues where on each iteration, our prediction is the last outcome of the
branch from the previous iteration.
In this example program, our branch predictor mispredicts four times out of eight, leading
to four flush penalties.
Modern high-performance branch predictors use two-bit prediction instead.
The motivation is that most branches are biased to either taken or not taken, and a one-bit
prediction usually changes its mind too quickly, leading to more mispredictions.
One-bit prediction is a similar structure except now each entry of the BHT is a two-bit
saturating counter.
This can be thought of as an FSM with four states, strong not taken and strong taken,
and weak not taken and weak taken.
If the prediction is currently strong taken or strong not taken, then we need to mispredict
twice in order to change our minds.
If we only mispredict once from a strong position, then we'll stick to our current prediction
but we're less confident about it.
In this table, capital letters indicate strong prediction and lowercase letter indicates
weak prediction.
Now going back to our example program, on the first iteration, let's say that our initial
prediction is weak not taken.
Then we find that the branch is actually taken.
So then we update our BHT entry to weak taken.
If the branch is taken again, that's now two times in a row.
We update our BHT entry to strong taken.
This yields a better misprediction rate since this program seems to be biased towards being
taken.
As we continue to execute the program, our two-bit prediction will fluctuate between
strong taken and weak taken, and it'll still be right most of the time.
Our last topic for this lecture is exceptions.
You may have seen exceptions when programming.
Perhaps it was arithmetic overflow or an unsupported instruction attempts to execute.
Other exceptions include page faults while accessing memory or an IO device had a status
change.
These surprises are called exceptions because they're not usual or common.
You can think of them as surprise procedure calls that get invoked at any time while executing
a program.
There are two types of exceptions, interrupts and traps.
Interrupts happen outside from the processor due to an event from IO devices.
Some IO devices may be polled instead of waiting for interrupts if they happen often enough.
Interrupts happen synchronously as a result of instructions at execution.
The hardware performs some preliminary actions, but then will rely on software to deal with
the exception.
The operating system implements a handler for each type of exception, which is placed at
a predefined memory location that is agreed upon by hardware and software.
In our MIPS architecture, the handler code for arithmetic overflow is located at the
address shown.
Instances ECE-552 will only focus on the hardware's role in exception handling.
MIPS performs three actions when an exception is detected.
First, it records the cause of the exception.
Second, it saves the PC of the instruction that caused the exception into the EPC register.
Finally, it writes the exception handler's PC to the PC.
This is essentially a special and surprising jump and link through though the return address
will be the EPC not register RA.
Here's our latest processor diagram before we add the changes required to support arithmetic
overflow exceptions.
Let's introduce two special registers, cause and EPC.
EPC will be set to the PC of the instruction that overflowed which is currently in the
execute stage.
These registers are not in the register file but are baked into the architecture.
Next, we need to flush the instruction from the pipeline as well as those in the decode
and fetch stages.
We're going to be returning from the handler and re-executing the function that caused the
overflow so without flushing we'd be executing those instructions twice.
This is the first time we've had to flush these two stages so we'll need muxes to clear
control signals just as we originally did with branching.
Lastly, we set the PC to the predefined exception handler address for arithmetic overflow.
Now our processor can catch exceptions and delegate the handling to software.
As we typically do, let's wrap up with some exercises to check our understanding.
Let's look at our five stage pipeline.
Perhaps when we only account for data hazards in our program, our average CPI is 1.2.
Now let's say our branches are resolved in the decode stage and that 30% of our instructions
are branches and 60% of them are taken.
Now the team is considering two options for resolving control hazards in our processor.
The first option is to implement a predict not taken policy which yields a clock period
of 300 microseconds.
The second option is to implement a branch predictor that achieves 90% accuracy but has
a higher clock period of 325 microseconds.
So pause the video and work it out.
Hint, compute the adjusted CPI for each and then use the clock period to determine the
new IPC.
In the first option, branches are resolved in the decode stage so we only have a one
cycle flush penalty when we mispredict.
Since 30% of the instructions are branches and 60 of them will incur this one cycle penalty,
we get a new CPI of 1.38 which at 300 microseconds results in 2,415 instructions per second.
For option 2, we only have a one cycle flush penalty on 10% of our branches barely bumping
our CPI to 1.23.
If we calculate the new wall clock time for an instruction, we can see that we can process
2,501 instructions per second or 86 more instructions than the basic predictor.
If your crucial workloads have 30% branches, the branch predictor should be one place that's
high on your list to research.
Now let's review branch delay slots.
Given this program, we put a no-op in the branch delay slot.
We prefer to keep our processor fully utilized.
Which of these instructions are legal to replace the no-op with?
You could ignore potential exceptions for this exercise.
Does this reordering result in a legal substitution?
Pause the video and reason about any data hazards.
Yeah, this is legal.
The branch on equal doesn't read the subtracts result and it needs to be executed anyway
so the program would still produce the same result.
How about the NOR instruction?
Does here and look for hazards?
Nope, this is not legal since there was a raw dependence on register S1 between the
NOR and branch equal instruction.
The branch needs the new value of S1 for its comparison and without this the program wouldn't
produce the same results.
How about the add instruction after the branch?
Can we shift that up into the branch delay slot?
Pause here.
And no, this is also not legal.
In the original program, the add was only executed if the branch was not taken.
Since it's now in a branch delay slot, it will get executed every time.
Also, it gets worse.
If the branch is taken, T1 now reads a different value of S1 in the OR instruction because
the add instruction was executed.
Okay, last one.
How about this?
Can we move the OR from T1 up to the main line?
Please pause again.
Actually, yes, this is legal.
This creates a right after right anti-dependence hazard because if we do not take the branch,
then add is going to overwrite S4 anyway.
In a way, this means that OR is a know-op if we do not branch, but it's useful work
if we do.
So it's not a win for both branch possibilities.